<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="2211">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 10, 2022</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00585572</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-2010-0037</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>H-2010-0037</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2014-1484</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>A534255</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>GERIATRICS AND ADULT</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2RF1AG027161-11A1</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1P30AG062715-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00585572</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Wisconsin Brain Donor Program</brief_title>
  <acronym>WBDP</acronym>
  <official_title>University of Wisconsin-Madison: Wisconsin Brain Donor Program (WBDP)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Wisconsin, Madison</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Wisconsin Brain Donor Program (WBDP) stores brain and other tissues/samples (e.g. blood&#xD;
      and CSF) from deceased individuals who have participated in longitudinal research studies, as&#xD;
      well as other select participants. These individuals have donated their tissues in order to&#xD;
      aid scientific research. Through the collection of central and peripheral nervous tissues as&#xD;
      well as (in select cases) skeletal muscle tissue, the WBDP strives to advance the knowledge&#xD;
      of diseases of memory disorders, such as Alzheimer's Disease. Brain donations are needed from&#xD;
      healthy individuals, as well as those affected by diseases of the nervous system.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Wisconsin Brain Donor Program (WBDP) of the University of Wisconsin-Madison School of&#xD;
      Medicine and Public Health is considered an investigator-initiated project. It was first&#xD;
      established in 1995 to promote teaching and research in neurodegenerative diseases. In 2009&#xD;
      the WBDP aligned itself with the research goals of the Wisconsin Alzheimer's Disease Research&#xD;
      Center (Wisconsin ADRC) in order to more effectively serve the research community. As a&#xD;
      result, the WBDP is part of a nationwide network of ADC/ADRC's (Alzheimer's Disease&#xD;
      Centers/Alzheimer's Disease Research Centers), funded by the National Institute on Aging that&#xD;
      exists to promote research on neurodegenerative diseases. However, the WBDP operates as an&#xD;
      independent research program under the direction of the WBDP and Wisconsin ADRC Principal&#xD;
      Investigators.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The WBDP provides approved researchers access to indefinitely-stored postmortem brain tissues&#xD;
      and post-mortem biospecimens (subject to the availability of remaining stock). Postmortem&#xD;
      biospecimens also include CSF and whole blood.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The WBDP staff promotes and educates the lay community on the importance of brain donation.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Goal/Objectives The overall goal of the WBDP is to function as a useful brain tissue and&#xD;
      biospecimen repository by distributing these materials to approved researchers studying&#xD;
      neurodegenerative diseases, particularly Alzheimer's disease (AD).&#xD;
&#xD;
      To achieve this goal, the WBDP has adopted the following overall objectives:&#xD;
&#xD;
        1. To serve as the tissue and biospecimen repository for the Wisconsin ADRC and Wisconsin&#xD;
           ADRC-affiliated studies. In this role, the WBDP will support collaborative research by&#xD;
           providing postmortem tissues, biospecimens, and genetic/genomic data for AD and other&#xD;
           neurodegenerative illnesses to approved researchers, whether at the University of&#xD;
           Wisconsin-Madison or other approved institutions. The investigators will also promote&#xD;
           data and sample sharing with ADRC Clinical Core, WRAP, and ADRC-affiliated studies such&#xD;
           as ADNI, DOD-ADNI, and ADNI Brain Bank.&#xD;
&#xD;
        2. To establish a registered group of individuals who intend to donate their brain tissue&#xD;
           and biospecimens after death for neurodegenerative-disease related research (the WBDP&#xD;
           Registry).&#xD;
&#xD;
        3. To oversee all aspects of brain tissue and biospecimen collection and management (their&#xD;
           procurement, indefinite storage, and distribution to approved researchers).&#xD;
&#xD;
        4. To collaborate with the National Alzheimer's Coordinating Center (NACC), the National&#xD;
           Centralized Repository for Alzheimer's Disease and Related Dementias (NCRAD) and similar&#xD;
           organizations, by providing coded biologic samples and data, inclusive of genetic data,&#xD;
           in order to further AD research.&#xD;
&#xD;
      Due to the nature of this study, no specific number of subjects is being proposed. This will&#xD;
      be an ongoing brain donation registry until funding is not renewed.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2026</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">9999</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Brain tissue, blood, cerebrospinal fluid, spinal cord, peripheral nerves, and skeletal&#xD;
      muscles, central/peripheral nervous tissue, as well as skeletal muscle tissue.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants agree to autopsy and brain/tissue/sample donation for research purposes only.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Is aged 18 years or older&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Falls into one of the following categories:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Current or previous study participants involved in the ADRC Clinical Core, WRAP&#xD;
                  study, or other select ADRC-affiliated studies, or donors of special&#xD;
                  circumstance, including healthy controls, if approved on a case-by-case basis by&#xD;
                  the WBDP PI. Please note, ADRC-affiliated studies are not inclusive of&#xD;
                  ADRC-affiliated industry-sponsored studies.&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Is a parent of either an ADRC Clinical Core or WRAP study participant, or is a&#xD;
                  spouse of a WRAP study participant.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  VA research subjects&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects with a medical condition/disease that would exclude them from the spectrum of&#xD;
             utility/interest to researchers as determined by a WBDP Neuropathologist:&#xD;
&#xD;
               1. Persons with Hepatitis B or C&#xD;
&#xD;
               2. Severe Traumatic Brain Injury&#xD;
&#xD;
               3. Positive CJD diagnosis&#xD;
&#xD;
               4. Persons with HIV/AIDS&#xD;
&#xD;
               5. Persons with brain tumors or blood clots that affect neurologic status, therefore&#xD;
                  creating a problem between diagnosing AD status and healthy status&#xD;
&#xD;
               6. Cancer that has metastasized to the brain&#xD;
&#xD;
               7. Radiation treatment to the head&#xD;
&#xD;
               8. Other infectious diseases that would be hazardous to staff handling the tissue&#xD;
&#xD;
               9. Prolonged ventilator dependency prior to death as determined by the&#xD;
                  Neuropathologist&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects who lack capacity to provide informed consent with no activated Power of&#xD;
             Attorney (POA) for Healthcare, activated POA for Research, or legal guardianship (if&#xD;
             not near death), or (if at or near death) have no spouse, parent, relative or friend&#xD;
             willing/able to complete consent and other donation paperwork.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects who otherwise have incomplete history or incomplete donation paperwork before&#xD;
             a recovery can begin.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Subjects younger than 18 years of age.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  An expected post-mortem interval (PMI) of greater than 16 hours for non-ADRC or&#xD;
             non-WRAP participants. PMI is the time between death and the anticipated time of brain&#xD;
             removal at autopsy. Families and recovery agencies are made aware of this time&#xD;
             constraint when consenting for the recovery process. If a patient becomes ineligible&#xD;
             due to PMI, the family and funeral home will be notified immediately. Diversions from&#xD;
             this exclusion can be made by a WBDP PI or Co-PI.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Medical conditions that would put researchers at risk.&#xD;
&#xD;
          -  Other contingencies, as determined by the PI, that make enrollment impractical or&#xD;
             unsafe.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Note: It is anticipated, based upon the younger age of our study cohorts, that significant&#xD;
        time may pass between WBDP registration and actual donation. The inclusion/exclusion&#xD;
        criteria will be reviewed and applied at time of donation. As a result, donated tissue&#xD;
        found to be unsuitable may be removed from the post-mortem tissue and biosamples&#xD;
        collection.&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shahriar Salamat, MD PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin Madison</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2022</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 26, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 2, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 3, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 13, 2022</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 13, 2022</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 14, 2022</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Normal Tissues/Brains</keyword>
  <keyword>Alzheimer</keyword>
  <keyword>Motor Neuron Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Control Volunteers</keyword>
  <keyword>Populations At Risk</keyword>
  <keyword>MCI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

