<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="2523">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 10, 2022</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00593138</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2006-p-001610</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00593138</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Dopamine Transporter Receptor Occupancy With Long-acting Dex-methylphenidate</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Open-label Study of Dopamine Transporter Receptor Occupancy With Long-acting Dex-methylphenidate (20 mg, 30 mg, and 40 mg) as Measured With C-11 Altropane in Healthy Adult Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objectives of this study are to document the pharmacokinetics of the adequacy of DAT&#xD;
      receptor occupancy d-MPH formulation in three doses (20 mg, 30 mg, and 40 mg) using PET&#xD;
      scanning with C-11 Altropane as the ligand across a range of times. It has been estimated&#xD;
      that MPH is effective when the average CNS DAT occupancy is 50% or greater. Focalin XR has&#xD;
      been shown to be clinically effective in an analog classroom as early as 1 hour and as late&#xD;
      as 12 hours. Therefore, it is hypothesized that the average DAT occupancy will be adequate&#xD;
      (50% or greater) at time periods corresponding to the times of clinical efficacy.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The first objective is to examine the onset of action by testing whether average DAT&#xD;
      occupancy will be adequate (50% or greater) at 1 hour after dosing for each dose tested (20&#xD;
      mg, 30 mg, 40 mg).&#xD;
&#xD;
      The second objective is to test the adequacy of average DAT occupancy in a range of later&#xD;
      times for each dose. The times chosen (8, 10 and 12 hours) correspond to times Focalin XR has&#xD;
      been shown to be clinically effective in an analogue classroom study. A range of times have&#xD;
      been chosen since, while effective at 12 hours, the degree of clinical effectiveness&#xD;
      decreased with later time periods. The adequacy of DAT occupancy across this range of time&#xD;
      periods will provide important details on the in vivo molecular action of the medicine at&#xD;
      periods of critical clinical activity.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The third exploratory objective is to examine a time period later then those previously&#xD;
      tested with the highest dose. Since the clinical effectiveness of Focalin XR has not been&#xD;
      tested out to 14 hours, it is unknown whether it is effective at 14 hours. If Focalin XR were&#xD;
      to be effective at 14 hours it would be more likely at the highest dose.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Stimulants have been shown to be very effective in the treatment of Attention Deficit&#xD;
      Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD). [1] Studies have shown that full day treatment is often&#xD;
      preferable to shorter treatment [2] and recent guidelines advise full day treatment. [3]&#xD;
      However, there are many barriers to giving multiple doses of short acting medicine. New&#xD;
      delivery systems have evolved to overcome tachyphylaxis and provide effective long-acting&#xD;
      treatment with a single pill. [4] One of the new formulations is the spheroidal oral drug&#xD;
      absorption system (SODAS). SODAS consists of capsules with two types of beads in a 1 to 1&#xD;
      ratio. One type of bead provides immediate release methylphenidate (IR MPH), and the other&#xD;
      type of bead consists of MPH coated with a polymer that delays release for 4 hours. SODAS MPH&#xD;
      has been shown to be effective in clinical studies [5]. However, the mechanism of action&#xD;
      remains unclear. While pharmacokinetic studies have shown a double pulse profile in the serum&#xD;
      [4], the central nervous system pharmacokinetics are unknown. Understanding the central&#xD;
      nervous system pharmacokinetic properties is critical for new drug development for ADHD,&#xD;
      especially for drugs of different lengths of action.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The d-MPH form has been shown to be the active enantiomer of MPH. Studies have shown that the&#xD;
      duration of action of d-MPH is longer than that of racemic MPH. Clinical studies of once a&#xD;
      day d-MPH has demonstrated efficacy in children, adolescents and adults with ADHD.&#xD;
      Understanding the central nervous system pharmacokinetic properties of the SODAS formulation&#xD;
      of the longer-acting (d) enantiomer will provide critical knowledge of its mechanism of&#xD;
      action.&#xD;
&#xD;
      The main target of MPH in the brain is the dopamine transporter (DAT) [6]. There is now an&#xD;
      exquisitely sensitive methodology to measure DAT occupancy using C-11 Altropane and Positron&#xD;
      Emission Tomography (PET) [7]. The time course of decay of the C-11 Altropane permits&#xD;
      repeated imaging, thus allowing documentation of the pharmacokinetics of DAT receptor&#xD;
      occupancy. A group at Massachusetts General Hospital has previously documented the central&#xD;
      nervous system pharmacokinetics of several psychiatric drugs using similar techniques [8-12].&#xD;
&#xD;
      To this end, this protocol seeks to document the pharmacokinetics of DAT receptor occupancy&#xD;
      of d-MPH using PET and C-11 Altropane. It has been estimated that MPH is effective when the&#xD;
      CNS DAT occupancy is 50% or greater. This aim of this study will be to measure CNS DAT&#xD;
      occupancies at extended time points after administration of d-MPH. This research will provide&#xD;
      novel and unique information toward a better understanding of the mechanism of action of&#xD;
      long-acting stimulant formulations to enable new drug development.&#xD;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>DAT occupancy from PET scan results</measure>
    <time_frame>each study visit</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">23</enrollment>
  <condition>Drug Binding to DAT Receptors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dex-methylphenidate</intervention_name>
    <description>The drug is administered as a capsule by mouth. Participants are assigned to receive either 20, 30 or 40 mg doses before each scan visit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Focalin XR</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Signed written informed consent to participate in the study.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Age: 18 -45, inclusive&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. If female, non-pregnant, non-nursing with a negative serum pregnancy test.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. Female subjects will agree to use an acceptable and effective form of birth control&#xD;
             during the course of their study participation.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Supine and standing blood pressure &lt; 150/90 mmHg.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. Heart rate, after resting for 5 minutes, within the range 46-90 beats/min.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Right handed.&#xD;
&#xD;
        Exclusion Criteria:&#xD;
&#xD;
          1. Diagnosis of any psychotic disorder, bipolar disorder, severe depression, severe&#xD;
             anxiety, or Autism. Subjects with mild mood, oppositional, conduct, and anxiety&#xD;
             disorders may be permitted to participate if considered appropriate by the&#xD;
             investigator.&#xD;
&#xD;
          2. Scores of Baseline Scales:&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Hamilton Depression Scale &gt; 12 (out of a possible 67 on the 21-item scale)[18]&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Beck Depression Inventory &gt; 19 (out of a possible 63 on the 21-item scale)[19]&#xD;
&#xD;
               -  Hamilton Anxiety Scale &gt; 21 (out of a possible 56 on the 14-item scale) [20]&#xD;
&#xD;
          3. Subjects with motor tics or with a family history or diagnosis of Tourette's Syndrome.&#xD;
&#xD;
          4. History of head trauma with loss of consciousness, organic brain disorders, seizures,&#xD;
             or neurosurgical intervention.&#xD;
&#xD;
          5. Any clinically significant chronic medical condition, in the judgment of the&#xD;
             investigator.&#xD;
&#xD;
          6. In the judgment of the investigator, has a mental impairment as evidenced by an I.Q.&#xD;
             &lt;75.&#xD;
&#xD;
          7. Exposure to dopamine receptor antagonists within the previous three (3) months.&#xD;
&#xD;
          8. Exposure to radiopharmaceuticals within four (4) weeks prior to PET scan.&#xD;
&#xD;
          9. Subjects receiving psychotropic medication including MAO inhibitors within the past 6&#xD;
             to 12 months.&#xD;
&#xD;
         10. Any clinically significant abnormality in the screening laboratory tests, vital signs,&#xD;
             or 12 lead ECG, outside of normal limits.&#xD;
&#xD;
         11. Any pre-existing structural cardiac abnormalities.&#xD;
&#xD;
         12. A history or known family history of long QT syndrome or QTc &gt;450 ms (males) or &gt;470&#xD;
             ms (females).&#xD;
&#xD;
         13. Any family history of cardiac sudden death.&#xD;
&#xD;
         14. QTc prolongation of QTc &gt; 450 ms (male) or 470 ms (female), hypertension or cardiac&#xD;
             arrhythmia, or increased heart rate for age in the judgment of the investigator at&#xD;
             screening.&#xD;
&#xD;
         15. A history of cardiac structural abnormality&#xD;
&#xD;
         16. Any woman of childbearing potential who is seeking to become pregnant or suspects that&#xD;
             she may be pregnant.&#xD;
&#xD;
         17. Subjects with a known recent history (within the past six (6) months) of illicit drug&#xD;
             or alcohol dependence.&#xD;
&#xD;
         18. Subjects diagnosed with glaucoma.&#xD;
&#xD;
         19. Subjects at risk for MPH toxicity (e.g. individuals with arrhythmias, coronary artery&#xD;
             disease, etc.).&#xD;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Spencer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>MGH</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 28, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 11, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 14, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 21, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 21, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 22, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Thomas J. Spencer, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Chief, Clinical and Research Program, Pediatric Psychopharmacology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Focalin XR</keyword>
  <keyword>Adult</keyword>
  <keyword>PET scan</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methylphenidate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexmethylphenidate Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

